Ethel Hale Freeman Papers, 1882-1917
Smith College Archives
Ethel Hale Freeman Papers
1882-1917
Freeman, Ethel Hale.
RG 42 UUID:0ae08ee2-0a5c-4256-bf35-32fe9b8e14f0
8 boxes (3.675 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Alumnae, Instructor, drama. Contains correspondence, materials related to Lend-a-Hand Dramatic Club, class notes, plays, photographs, and memorabilia.
Ethel Hale Freeman graduated from Smith College in 1902. After graduation, she studied at the Art School of the Boston Museum of Fine Arts, and received her M.A. from Smith in 1915. After some years spent serving as dramatic coach for the Wellesley Shakespeare Society and the Players of Newton, she came to Smith to teach elocution and modern drama from 1911 to 1917. She also taught spoken English and Shakespeare in a University extension course in Greenfield, Massachusetts. Between 1917 and 1925, Freeman taught English at the Lee School in Boston, and from 1924 to 1933, was an instructor at Dana Hall and Pine Manor in Wellesley. She was active in many forms of the arts, including music, sculpture, and the theater. Although she grew up in West Newton, she spent many happy summers on her old farm in Ashfield. Freeman died in Essex, Connecticut on February 26, 1963.
The Ethel Hale Freeman Papers span a period from 1882 to 1917. Much of the material is from her time as a professor at Smith. The information regarding her personal life is largely confined to her correspondence with her family during two trips to Europe, the first in 1905-1906 and the second in 1908-1909. A large portion of the collection contains correspondence and materials documenting her involvement in various organizations, particularly the Lend-a-Hand Dramatic Club. The folders are arranged alphabetically by subject, and the collection is composed of correspondence, class notes, plays, photographs, memorabilia books, and other general items such as music scores and sketches.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. General
II. Correspondence
III. Class Notebooks
IV. Memorabilia
V. Lend-a-Hand Dramatic Club
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
History of the Collection
Search Terms
Freeman, Ethel Hale.; Smith College Faculty.; Smith College--Students.; Comstock, Ada Louise.; Seelye, Laurenus Clark, 1837-1924.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925; Grenfell, Wilfred Thomason, Sir, 1865-1940; Mendenhall, Thomas Corwin
- Series I. GENERAL
  The first series, General, contains miscellaneous information on Freeman's life. This includes details about her Spoken English class at Smith, photographs, her undergraduate achievements, how she came to be appointed Instructor of Elocution, and some tidbits of biographical information. It appears that she was very interested in dramatics and theater, two programmes from productions she attended are in the collection, which explains why she taught Elocution. Elocution is what later evolved to be the Theater Department here at Smith. Thus, Freeman was essentially one of the pioneers in that area.
  - Appointment 1911-17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Data 1915-50 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Drama Room 1913, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - High School 1898 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jokes and Lampoons 1909, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Phi Beta Kappa Society 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs 1900-02, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Religion Class Notes 1911-17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sigma undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sketches undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Spoken English - Examinations, etc. 1915-17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Spoken English - Lecture Notes undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Spoken English - Reports, Elocution 1911-17, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II. CORRESPONDENCE
  The second series is composed primarily of Correspondence between Freeman and various people. A mix of personal and formal letters, handwritten and typed, can be found. Her correspondance covers both her personal and professional lives, from her letters to her family during two early trips to Europe to her communications with people in the Smith College community (such as Presidents Seelye and Burton) and celebrities like Helen Keller. Also included in the series are letters from Freeman's aunt, Harriet E. Freeman, who accompanied her on two of her European trips, to various members of the Freeman family. The series also contains some newspaper articles and postcards.
  - Bonstelle, Jesse to EHF 1916-17 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Burton, Marion L. to EHF 1911-17 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Comstock, Ada L. to EHF 1917-18 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Emerson, Ellen Tucker to EHF 1913, 17 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Freeman, Caroline from EHF 1905-1908 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Freeman, Ethel Hale to Margaret Grierson 1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Freeman, Harriet Clark from EHF 1905-1909 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Round Robin letters: Freeman, Harriet E. to EHF 1906 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Freeman, Helen Hunt from EHF 1905-1909 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ganong, William Francis to EHF 1915 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Grenfell, Wilfred T. to EHF 1928-29 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Hale, Ellen Day to EHF 1904 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Hoyt, Hildegrade to EHF 1912 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Kapp, Marie F. to EHF 1913 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Keller, Helen to EHF 1902 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Kiernan, George to M.L. Burton 1912 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Libby to Miss Neeson undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - McClellan, Katherine Elizabeth to EHF 1908, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Mendenhall, Thomas Corwin to EHF 1960 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Newcomb, Edith Turner from EHF (Christmas carols) 1902, 1925-27, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Notman, Winifred to EHF 1913 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Pomeroy, Helen Jackson to EHF 1912 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - re: portrait of Seelye, L. Clark, letter from LCS 1908, 1910-11, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Shakespeare Memorial Theatre to EHF 1934 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Smith, Mary P. Wells to EHF 1916 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Wardwell, Eunice (Remington) to EHF 1913 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Series III. CLASS NOTEBOOKS
  Freeman's Class Notebooks document much of her undergraduate career at Smith. Her notes appear to be neat and clearly labeled. Some subject, such as Dramatics and Zoology, contain not only her notes but the textbooks she used as well. For her dramatics class, she read The Adventure of Lady Ursula, a book that also contains pictures of characters in costumes. Freeman has minimal class notes for this subject. A lot of her notes are from her literature classes, and these are meticulously organized into different notebooks, each lecture beginning on another page. Freeman's Zoology notes are less well organized, and this folder also contains the book she used in class. For her Themes and Verse class, the stack of loose-leaf papers she took notes on seem to have just been bundled together, a contrast to the neat notebooks she kept for Literature.
  - General 1899-1902 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dramatics 1899-1902 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Literature 1899-1902 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Literature (cont.) 1899-1902 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Science - Zoology 1899-1902 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Themes and Verse 1899-1902 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series IV. MEMORABILIA
  The fourth series contains music scores composed by Freeman, photo albums, and a very large Memorabilia book. Most of the musical scores are in notebooks, while others are on loose sheets of paper. These are labeled with the title of the piece, but some appear to be messy and look like drafts. The album contains a great number of photographs, all of which have the names of the people in the photo and the date listed at the bottom. Most of the photos are of people, although there are a few of scenery. Freeman's memorabilia book appears to be a very large compilation of mementos and keepsakes from her college years. Notes, cards, articles, ribbons, and even matchboxes are all included. There is no apparent order to all these objects, but they all appear to have personal meaning to Freeman herself. It gives one insight into the numerous activities she participated in while a Smith College student.
  - MEMORABILIA BOOK (Box 4)
  - Music Scores 1922, 1923, 1935,1936, 1939, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Music Scores (cont.) 1931, 1953, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photograph Album 1904-11 (Box 5)
- Series V. LEND-A-HAND DRAMATIC CLUB
  Freeman was heavily involved in the Lend-a-Hand Dramatic Club, an organization that promoted philanthropic interest in young people by getting them involved in the dramatic society, the profits of which go to charity. Examples of charities the organization has donated to are the Boston Floating Hospital, Blind Babies Home, Hale Endowment Fund, and Boston Normal School. A list of the Club's receipts and expenses reveal that most of the plays performed make a profit of over $500. There are also several notebooks of minutes from meetings. Almost all of the plays performed by the Club are contained in this series. While not all plays have copies of the scripts available, most have copies of the programs and some even have articles on it. This is obviously a project Freeman devoted much of her time to, being one of the founders of the organization.
  - General
    - Characters undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Constitution and By-Laws 1910, 1912, 1914, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Donations 1907-25 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - General 1903-28 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Meetings 1911-18, 1925, 1928, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Membership 1908, 1910, 1912, 1915 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Minutes 1909-11, 1914-15, 1922-28 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Music Scores undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Photographs undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Publications 1907, 1913, 1915, 1916, 1922-29, 1936, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Reports - Annual 1902, 1907, 1912-13, 1922, 1929, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Reports - Treasurer's 1913-25 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Shakespeare Trophies 1900, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Songs 1908 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Plays, A-L
    - Adventures of Lady Ursula 1903 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Alice at Smith undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - As You Like It 1902 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Beau Brummel 1921 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Brer Rabbit 1926 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Christmas Carol 1909, 1914 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Christmas Pageant 1920 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Doctor of Alcantara 1916 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Eight Cousins 1924 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Fliveretta 1924 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Galatea 1921 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Gondoliers 1911 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Gringoire 1907 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Hamlet 1907 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Heidi 1925 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Iolanthe 1910 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Land of Heart's Desire 1907 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Little Lord Fauntleroy 1918 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Little Men 1923 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Little Women 1924 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - The Locket 1910 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Love in a Garret undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Plays, M-Z
    - Master Skylark 1928 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Midsummer Night's Dream 1905 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Monsiere Beaucaire 1907, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - H.M.S. Pinafore undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Naughty Little Princess 1912. 1921 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Playboy of the Western World 1922 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Prince and the Pauper 1919 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Purple and Fine Linen 1917 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Professor's Love Story 1910 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Romeo and Juliet 1908 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Ruddy Gore 1913 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs 1920 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Speed undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Taming of the Shrew 1904 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Twelfth Night 1914 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Workhouse Maid Rosalind 1915 (Box 8, Folder 16)